um let's start uh today's lecture uh
today's lecture is about feature uh
extraction
um I will try to kind of introduce some
of the basic of the feature extraction
uh and also try to provide in some of
the uh the latest Technologies uh for
the feature extraction uh but in this
lecture I try to kind of remain uh that
basically the uh uh the fundamental fure
extraction part and this part will be
the uh main topic in the the coding
assignment one which will be released in
the uh the Wednesday so
please uh check uh this uh lecture
carefully okay so last time we discussed
about uh the speech uh recognition can
be uh divided to the several
components like for example by using the
the Su Ru uh conditional Independence
assumption and product rule we can
actually factorize each of the problem
to the acostic modeling Le language
modeling in the hmm based system and
even that the end to end system we
usually separating the feature
extraction and other part and today uh
we will talk about the feature
extraction part but high level
what they are doing is converting the
waveform to the other continuous Vector
so that's a kind of a high level
part and the I have a couple of uh the
remark for today's the feature
extraction so first the speech
extraction is I think not only for
speech many of the area generally very
empirical so this part the speech
feature extraction is for me the quite
empirical and quite engineering and the
reason of the current form of the future
extraction logma filter bank is actually
the based on the many aspects of course
we should get a better performance but
not only for that it should be very
first it should be kind of online it
should be the a good compatibility and
so on based on this kind of various
factors a current the feature extraction
is formed so some people may asking why
we use you know the F transform why use
we use you know other transform and so
on um I usually have a several answers
to the the the uh the satisfy your
questions but generally it's not a
perfect answer simple answer it's
because again the this try to satisfy
all this kind of requirement and then
engineering the this kind of a current
solution is uh the uh introdu so this is
quite kind of difficult
that to explain it and also each
operation is based on the signal
processing so I sure that many people
here actually also have a signal
processing background but some of them
are not but uh in this lecture we do not
kind of uh the Deep deeply kind of uh
dig into the the signal processing part
so just a basic operation like the
shortterm H transformation and so is
find other kind of knowledge and the
some of the empirical part is not only
for the this kind of property but it's
also kind of motivated by the human
auditory system that is also one part
that the making the kind of this feature
extion part to be a little bit
complicated okay so uh let's move to the
uh the the uh actual process so the goal
of this uh the feature extraction part
is actually to convert the the web form
signal to this uh the the spectral uh
the
representation and actually I want to
ask which one is
more you guys find some
patterns uh the left one and the right
one which one do you think would have a
more visible patterns
yeah thank you for having a straight
word answer some people actually say
that the next one has more patterns yeah
I I also think that the right side has
some pattern but it's also based on the
knowledge that you know we know some
kind of the spectral structure uh so but
anyway the the feature extraction is uh
making the the feature to be more uh the
the the uh the tractable and the
this is actually quite the um um related
to our intuition instead of having a low
other signal which has a lot of noises
maybe we can find some kind of better
representation which generally actually
the after the visualization it becomes
the more patterns which means that the
the the visualization and the the
feature instructions are quite kind of
thetive and actually uh the this uh the
web form is not easy for human to read
but some very trained people actually
read
spectrogram and then could find that
this one is you know two and so on by I
I cannot do that but some other people
actually could do it this means that
this spectral feature has the some
information about the
the text form and so on
okay so this is kind of our Target how
to make that kind of a waveform to be
the
more the more the visible patterns of
the features and let's move to the uh
the the the uh the process one by one
first the what is a web
form so web form is a kind of a the
converting the sound
pressure uh the and then that kind of
sound pressure vibration is the captured
by the the electric signal so we just
kind of the uh the the purely recording
the the the sound pressure that becomes
the weave form and since you know that
once we kind of converting this to the
the the electric form and then that the
we can actually you know generating it
again and we can actually hearing it
right which means that this wave the
pressure sound pressure information is
the efficient to capture all the kind of
sound information but this one is quite
really uh the the dense uh the feat the
representation in terms of the time just
having a one dimensional wave form and
having a very kind of a dense uh the the
representation across the time and in
this lecture I mostly uh focus on the
single Channel cases
but of course that we have a lot of
cases that the uh the uh the webform can
be
represented several uh the the signals
for example the the most the the the
famous the common example is that our
years has two which means that we
usually capture two signals and Alexa
has seven microphones uh and so on
actually it's better to capture various
kind of information uh but generally uh
in this kind of lecture we just more
focus on the single
Channel okay but actually this sound
pressure is a continuous
value continuous function so it it was
not easy to actually directly doing it
with the uh the the the computer so we
have to have a discretization process
the
discretization in the uh
time domain and
discretization we call it as a
quantization in the the amplitude domain
we actually using this kind of a two
ways of the discretization the sampling
and quantization to the make the speech
the signal to be the friendly for the
computer and then the the the question
here is you know how often we kind of
ass sample the data and how how much we
kind of quantize the
amplitude and that's was the so-called
sampling
rate so nowadays the everyone may use
the a lot of kind of audio device and
then some of you may heard that the the
sampling rate like generally 48 khz is
for the DVD sounds right and the 441
Point KZ for the the the the CD sound I
guess it's now that everyone almost
using this 48 KZ but it's actually uh
this uh the of course you know higher is
better right to the model there uh the
the the very precise web form but but at
the same time you know uh the we don't
need so much the high resolution so
there are lot of kind of part study and
it turns out that the another 20 is fine
for speech by the way the the whole
other sound like a music and so on
higher frequency is important so that's
why still you know the DVD sound and so
on is using a 48 kilal but for speech
cases actually 16 kilal or 20 kilal is
fine so that the actually the mostly in
our kind of uh the the uh the the speech
of the the recognition application we
are using a 16 khz
sampling by the way there's still the
lot of data from the 8 KZ sampling which
is the the telephone the cases since you
know we used to be have a lot of kind of
issue in the band withs you know we want
to anyway compress the data and so on so
the at health is
actually significantly uh the the uh the
the the degrader quality you know the
the thecenter kind of a the high
resolution audio from the DVD and the
telephone telephone speech is actually
quite distorted right but it's still
audible right lot of actually uh the
experiment and then we finally decide 8K
Health it's a kind of a minimum
reasonable the sampling rate uh
to sound so due to that kind of a large
the application in the telephone we
still have a lot of 8 khz example but
mostly nowadays we actually using a 16
Kilz and then the uh the discretization
quantization part we usually using a 16
bit so please remember by that 16 16
that is a kind of basic uh the uh the
the the the discretization for the
waveform and there are actually lot of
uh the format uh for the the web form
and the uh the mostly uh I think many
people are using a different wave the
format right
uh of course Web format people have
heard that right how many people have
heard Web format W
yeah uh
MP3 okay
not so many people okay actually more
than I expected
yeah
yeah um these three are mostly used in
the speech uh the processing but we also
have a lot of the other format depending
on the kind of purpose or depending on
the uh the the conventions uh the end
one so actually speech data uh the we
also using the format called sphere
SP have you ever heard this
format oh you're
good maybe you are old I'm
kidding yes sphere format is used for
the the old speech data and it's
actually made by n uh and the uh but
still the many of the famous database is
sphere format so we actually have to use
it like uh we will explain that in the
in the the some of the following the
lectures but the T me the ti digit War
Journal very famous database is actually
based on the SP format SP
format okay so uh the this is a kind of
uh most of the uh the the Web format and
then the uh but again that we usually
using 16 khz and 16 bit and many of the
recent recording is 44.1 or 48 khz so
the we have actually have to convert it
and the down sampling is actually quite
easy that we can just using a many of
the tools uh and so on and I often use
the socks but probably people here FM
maybe more famous uh but H okay maybe I
can also ask how many people have ever
used socks so
okay and
FM oh actually not so so different yeah
usually these two are used uh the since
it's very kind of the uh the Linux or
other Unix or other other
operation the system uh friendly uh and
so on so the usually we using the socks
to down sample to the shifting your
and uh By the way when we have a 8 Kilz
cases uh we usually up sample and then
make it the 16 K and then dealing with
it but upsampling is actually not very
recommended because the there's nothing
if that in terms of the the from the the
the 8 to 16 KS information so it's just
kind of the the interpolate to get such
kind of high frequency which is not very
accurate so uh the upsampling is not the
the recommended way but as an easy
solution we usually do
it okay so now we know the waveform so
let's move to the the feature extraction
part now we know this part right and the
feature extraction I just put it as a
kind of single box and you know many
people may know that you know they just
using the M filter Bank M she it's
actually sounds like just one tool right
but it's actually quite complicated
uh we have at least five blocks by the
way I usually kind of skipping the
preemphasis which is also includ in the
the coding assignment so it's going to
be like actually six but anyway that we
usually have this five to five operation
or four operation uh depending on the
our application but it depend on how to
kind of count stft for example sdfd is
the compos of the framing uh the the
uh and the uh the the
multiplication the of the
uh the F transform and so on so it can
be actually split to two or three but
anyway let's make one block at the sdfd
and next then that we going to have
taking the magnitude and then we will
perform the log M filtering and then uh
H sorry uh M filtering and then taking
the log and the last part is kind of
optional I will briefly explain each
part of one by one uh but actually it's
changing the the the number to the
interesting kind of a domain so first uh
the the uh the sample is that after the
discretization it is just a discrete
onedimensional
symbol and then after the stfd it
becomes a complex and some dimension
uh the the feature and after the the
magnitude operation it becomes the
positive vector and then M filtering is
applied and the finally uh the uh the
log operation is
applied and that's and I will visualize
each component plus again you know this
part
that yeah fine
uh anyway this is a kind of maybe I can
try whether it's a or not
there there the system is seem to
working just a two so this The Weave
form first are the Performing the
short-term Cent transform and then this
is actually complex so it's not easy to
visualize but if we kind
of using it the real and imaginary part
it becomes like this
there's some pattern here by the way but
the mostly not so much
pattern uh let's take our
energy here there's some
pattern but not so
much and then after that we take uh the
uh the male filter and then sorry this
is actually after the M filter m m
filtering as well and then uh the
finally we take a log and then it's a
little bit more visible so the feature
that are coming from this one to this
one this one this one so this is a kind
of a process that as as I said it can be
little bit more visible more pattern has
more pattern than the the usual uh uh
and so on and the last part uh DCT is
important to get the the feat that is
fitting to the gaussian model but now
that the gaussian is not used anymore so
I didn't fully kind of explain this
part okay so uh that's the kind of a
high level overview inside again inside
this kind of the feature extraction is
having a several kind of the layers and
it's actually having a several
operations and I will talk about the
each of the component one by
first part shortterm H transform so this
part is actually try to capture the
periodic component which is the most
basic uh operation of the webform not
only for the speech any of the kind of
the sound analysis that we usually
performing the the web
form shortterm the the F Transformer and
then uh this uh is basically
based on the the configuration basically
we try to kind of the capture the around
the 10 to 100 millisecond of the
periodic signal and why I we kind of
focus on this kind of a scale this is a
kind of a the scale that the p is
changing so that's why we kind of using
this order of the the time scale and
from the 16 the Kilz the the the order
of the sampling order of the time
signal so this part uh is uh the
basically uh the we just kind of the
getting the weighted some
operation of the original
signal uh by using some kind of
convolutional
operation with the exponential other
information and this is actually
imaginary a complex number so that this
the part is actually the periodic signal
and then by using this operation we can
actually get the the periodic the signal
uh the end so one so this is actually
the basic shortterm H the transform but
it's actually having a lot of by unknown
uh the part plus what is this weight how
to decide this this one this one is
actually the the exponential inside n is
kind of a
summation the index so it's cannot be
the uh the it can be actually the
marginalized and F is a kind of index of
the frequency so the important part is
to uh the provide this the weight
function and then we actually having a
lot of parameter for here like we could
use a gaussian we could use humming or
we could use huning and so on basically
uh this the operation is
to approximate this summation uh of the
minus infinity to Infinity to the kind
of uh the the range that we can actually
handle so that we can compute it uh in
the uh the uh the in our kind of the
normal computational scale rather than
infinity and then this kind of a
size is that becomes the the size that
we want to kind of get the signal the
periodic information from the signal so
this becomes a kind of a usually 25
millisecond or 32 millisec and depending
on our kind of application and so on so
by taking this
operation uh we could actually convert
the signal uh from the waveform to this
this kind of the
representation and again this are the
the representation I just using the real
and imaginary part since this is a
complex number but usually we discard
the Page information and just only
taking the power and then that will be
use for our speech the future and so on
I will explain that why kind of we take
the the power and the discard phase and
so on later
but anyway I am expecting the some of
the people having a good signal
processing uh the background could
follow it and some people that having a
CS background and don't have so much
experience the signal processing may not
fully follow this prod and then I
actually prepare this SL actually this
operation
is quite similar to the
comosition operation uh the actually we
can WR this one other other compulation
operation in in p and so on and then the
the the weight usually convolution
weight for example this part uh is
actually estimated in the neural network
operation but in the the shortterm H
transform actually this part is designed
by our kind of the the known operation
again this one is known operation and
this part is is also using the humming
or huning to make this part to
be getting the periodical signal in the
comol operation but anyway if you're not
very familiar with this operation please
think this is one of the comilation
operation and by the way uh there are
lot of actually activities uh why not
you know replacing this operation as
actual
convolution uh the convolution work so
many people actually working on try to
replacing the uh this the stft operation
in the other convolutional neural
network other kind of
research P so this is called runable the
front end so
on okay so after we get this kind of a
the the feature uh for each kind of a
time frame we actually are using the the
shift operation to uh process this the
gaussian uh not gaussian sorry the
humming uh window to get the kind of
stft operation for the some specific
kind of time frame and then we actually
applying this one to the next frame and
so on so note that this are the the
size usually it is 25 millisecond and
this shift is usually different and the
shift is kind of less than 10
millisecond uh less than half of the
window size in general otherwise we
actually missing the information by kind
of taking a very large St
yes
um now that I talked about you know uh
the 25 millisecond as a kind of a
general window size and the 10
millisecond is a shift or maybe some
cases I also often use 32 millisecond
the window size and 8 millisecond for
the shift side depending on the kind of
our configurations and so on but I am
actually speech more for the speech side
of the people so usually using a
millisecond uh but the audio people they
may also use a millisecond but they use
the Point sample point so this is a
little bit kind
of give you make some confusions to you
guys so to avoid you that I just having
this kind of a equation for example if
we using a 16 khz sampling cases and
then 25 millisecond
window uh this means that
16,000 time 25 Divided 1,000 so it's
actually have
400 point at per
second part the uh the power window
sorry the power window
okay uh and opposite case is if we using
the say
512 are the uh the point window size
which means that actually the by
dividing by the sampling grade it
becomes 32 millisecond so I actually
want you to be familiar with this
conversion uh so that you know uh some
people are discussing with you about the
the speech and audio processing some
people may use that the I use the 520
Point window size or I use a 25
millisecond the window size and and we
should actually convert it in our brain
so the first actually short quiz
question is actually about it so the
five 12 point
Windows the corresponding to the how
many millisecond that is the kind of the
first short qu uh yeah yeah by the way
the answer is 64
millisecond so uh the 100 m 100 36
million uh and of course the 100,000
hours is a scale that we usually make a
commercial product and the the amount of
the the number of frames goes to billion
actually yeah 36 billion and then the
some of you might heard the open air
recently the released the speech
condition system called The Whisper
which is using
680,000 hours so P correspond to
20050 billion of course still you know
that compared with super large language
model uh this are the we didn't go to
the scale of the the tum but we are
usually actually working on this scale
at least you know the the the 10 to 100
million is the usual
for speech uh the processing so that's
why I really want you guys to apply to
the AWS credit and some other GPU
otherwise that you couldn't actually
it's okay for the uh uh the term project
but the uh even for the uh the coding
assignment you guys may need that to
handle the the order of the million or
10 million samples so it's better to do
that and the yeah I also calculate I'm
just a curious you know uh the how much
so the one year is like this8 8,000 so
10,000 hour right so open whisper is
actually using a 70 years of the speech
it's actually not so much right
yeah we yes the the it's can be you know
more than the one person's kind of the
the the the the using the speech but
it's actually just one person the the
little bit not more than the one person
the the the speaking speech uh the in
their entire life but just two or three
right and everywhere you know we are
speaking so billion of the people are
speaking then then we actually have a
tons of speech so yeah uh that probably
this numbers can be increased more and
more uh in the
future okay so uh the uh that's about
stft shortterm Hood transform yes so
next part is uh the uh after taking the
kind of a power uh
operation uh uh it is uh uh looks like
this by the way uh the the signal energy
is having a very different dynamic range
so just checking the kind of energy is
not always good in terms of making it
visible so we usually actually taking
the log uh to make this kind of to be
visible uh now the actually power is
having this kind of a pattern but we
actually empirically know that the lower
the frequency of the signal should have
more speech information so uh this is
actually lot of kind of the perceptual
experiment uh we found that the
uh this the lower the signal should have
more kind of emphasized so to do that
the people actually using the M the
filter bank and I will quickly explain
it but mostly the uh the the uh the the
M fil Bank sounds like a very
complicated that's actually very
complicated but as an operation what we
are doing is just a matrix operation and
then how to kind of get this Matrix is a
kind of M so please remember that so
first uh we try to use the kind of
different scale than the normal uh the
the frequency scale that's again based
on the kind of perceptual study that we
are having a good uh the the the uh the
the the ability to get the information
in the lower the the energy of the
signal so we try to imitate this kind of
a function and then the the people
actually come up with several the
version of the the function one of them
like this uh so this may not be so much
the intuitive so that we just have a
kind of a a figure here so this is
actually the the male scale so as you
see that you know uh the the the
beginning of the part is almost linear
right almost we just the passing the
information that the frequency but the
higher and then actually the uh this uh
the male uh information is actually not
so much increased so this is actually
nonlinear uh the the the operation to
consider to emphasize uh not to
emphasize kind of having a
more having extracted information in the
lower frequency side but the smearing
the uh the the higher the frequency side
because it's not super important
so this is a kind of a log sorry
M frequency transform and actually this
is uh not easy and what we are usually
doing is uh the two first the set kind
of a maximum and minimum the frequency
uh the the uh the Leng and then the
taking that kind of a this kind of line
equal line in the male the scale equal
line in the m scale corresponding to the
nonlinear scale in the the normal uh the
spectral scale and then taking the the
triangle filters to actually the compute
the the smearing part the end so it is a
little bit complicated but I prepare
some of the references so if you guys
are interested please also check it and
this part is not included other uh the
uh the our coding assignment this the
operation is already prepared by the
way uh even is that true right that we
have a b Matrix already yes but again
the the this the function is making a
kind of a the low frequency to have the
more inform the the information almost
like original information comes from the
the Spectrum but the higher part is the
basically weighted sum so it's have a
kind of long like the line here means
that this kind of the weighted some
operation weight is kind of represented
here so this means that the high
frequency part uh is kind of a
information is basically saring we still
get some information but it's not very
important so that we actually are taking
this kind of our the SM smearing uh
operation uh and so on and the uh the
finally uh as it is actually uh the
performed in the energy the the power
domain and then finally taking a l and
then we call this operation as L fil b
or some people just calling fbank but
this mean the L fil Bank uh uh and uh so
on and the uh let's uh the uh discuss uh
about the log power versus L M fi Bank
actually left side is the power and
right side is the m field Bank uh first
this one has a many dimensions right
until uh
500 but this one is actually the the
80 so just with compressor information
the the the filter the uh stft
information is still very redundant for
us so this is one operation and the
other is as I mentioned we emphasize
more in the lower uh spectral
information and the higher resolution
still have some information but it's
kind of smearing information that is
kind of empirically uh the very good for
uh the speech uh processing so this uh
operation is
finally obtained with this kind of other
the uh the the more patterned and more
complex uh representation and so on and
then I also had a lot of questions about
it first you all why we discard the
phase information uh the why taking the
uh the uh Power operation so on so the
answer is perceptually we actually don't
need so much for the phase information
plus you know phas information is
actually just shifting the kind of a a
signal right even it is you know shifted
or not shape is not different so
perceptually it's not very important uh
also by the way she the pH also
sometimes has some kind of
spectral structures and so it is
actually not completely true but
empirically the yes and actually uh this
uh the logic does not apply to the mar
Chanel cases in the M Chanel cases pH
information is super important we
actually consider the phe difference and
then we can actually find some where the
the sound comes from and then we could
actually just easily separate the signal
and so on so the the pH information is
is not super important in the single
Channel cases but for if we performing
the M Channel cases it is very
important and the other frequent
question uh the H we we know multiple
other cool the the the functions to
conver the signal to that more kind of
pattern information like instead of
using me we can use a b or some other
kind of a measure that is that come from
the the perception but we can also use a
wave or whatever and so on but again
empirically uh there is not so much
difference just you know having some
other dimension reduction and the the
emphasizing the low the the frequency
signal is good enough feature so due to
that there still I think it started to
be used I don't know the 90 80s or
something like that but still are the
many people are still using the L filter
bank or
mscc uh and next the question this is
also very frequent question why we use a
humming we should use a huning or we
should why we have a lot of you know uh
the the the shift sze and so on there
are lot of actually hyper parameters
uh exist in the uh the future extraction
uh the endodon and actually uh this part
is very complicated and some cases also
the the filter Bank the calculation
requires some kind of rounding and so on
rounding and Edge processing and so on
is actually the slightly different
depending on the kind of implementation
so usually I couldn't actually reproduce
exactly same result as the
the the several other Library like the
BR and so on because of the very small
difference in the many hyper parameters
uh in the feature extraction
side and the the last question I often
had is that the M filter Bank what kind
of information do we have and actually I
say that most of the information except
for the the special information that I
mentioned the direction uh the uh
information uh m is actually initially
used for the perceptual uh the the uh
measure uh the for the speech
recognition but it actually turns out
that it is also used for the speaker
recognition and so and surprisingly it
is also used for the audio sound event
the problem and so on so even it is
design for the speech so uh the the
filter bank is M filter Bank actually
has a lot of
information uh and the uh the the the I
would say that the
empirically the many reason but just
kind of a good compressed information
and sufficient feature speech feature
that is a kind of meld that is my kind
of a personal opinion and I would
recommend you to actually also talk to
you know many other speech people here
uh that they may also have a lot of
opinion about you know why we still
using M and so on but my kind of
experience is that again very good
compression and still having some speech
speech uh not speech only some features
yeah very kind of abstract answer that
to me yeah based on my
experience okay so I will quickly also
go through the other kind of advanced
feature processing which is Delta
feature the mean
normalization so uh the Delta feature is
by the way one of the the the technique
that came from
Japan famous technique came from Japan
that um so later we actually are using a
lot of conditional Independence
assumption and then actually this one
from this one to this one it is very
different right this is like let's say
gaan mixture a deep neuron Network and
so on and then generating the kind of
speech and so on this one is actually
con in all kind of joint relationship
while it's actually cutting all the kind
of the dependency for the right side
right but the as a kind of modeling we
often use this one to make the kind of a
computational the complexity the smaller
but again this one is uh doesn't
consider kind of a relationship of the
feature so we
usually cannot capture the the long
context information for this kind of
approximation and then one possibility
is extending the feature to kind of
including the uh the the surrounding
features like a previous features and
the next features and then making it as
a kind of new feature that is what we
usually do but this actually has a kind
of very high correlation in the feature
so that is actually especially not very
good for the gaussian cases although
deep near cases it is not
so not so kind of problematic so instead
we actually using the uh the data
questions and then using it as a kind of
additional feature and it turns out that
this kind of representation is that
Dimension is not so much changed but
this one has more information than the
this kind of concatenating three
features so this are the data feature
originally was quite often used in the
speech processing but after deep neur
Network this kind
method is not so much
use and the next one is a mean
normalization so this
operation uh that is quite I think
people are familiar with the in terms of
the the the people may also call
whitening or whatever right this is just
kind of a subtracting the mean this is
the kind of the in terms of the machine
learning perspective statistical
perspective we just try to kind of
remove the bias right but in the speech
processing this actually has more
meanings so actually the the the
original signal is the the often
convoluted by the room impa response and
so on or many of the kind of the
compolation Distortion actually happens
everywhere in our world like if we also
even kind of at a call in the phone this
also usually has some kind of comol
Distortion which is actually changing
the voice devation changing the voice
right and if you use other pH that this
slightly change the voice and so right
this is comes from this comosition
operation and then this one we want to
remove and fortunately after the
shortterm F transform if this kind of
comilation distortion is not very long
it's actually represented as a
multiplication it has a lot of
approximation but anyway it can be
approximated to be represented at a
multiplication and then after this
multiplication taking the log and then
this part can be actually separated uh
the compolation part and the the
original Source part is actually
separated in the addition and look at
this one this one is actually doesn't
depend on the time so by taking the kind
of a mean normalization we could
actually removing this Channel distory
show so me normalization again in
general to remove the bias which is very
important for machine learning but in
speech cases it actually has a more kind
of concrete meaning we could actually
remove the channel distorion and so
on okay so and then the last two slide
is just but quickly you know it's more
for the classical signal processing but
the what's happening in the the uh the
research phase I want to explain first
part is that as I mentioned log fil bank
is actually still basic operation like
you know shortterm F transform is a
complex but linear transformation uh and
also comis the com comosition linear
transformation taking the power is also
basic operation and the male is actually
as I mentioned is written as a matrix
and taking the log all operation uh the
comosition uh the power male log is
actually basic function so we could
actually get a derivative by the way so
that we actually putting some kind of
learnable parameter somewhere in this
kind of operation or we can also are
actually using the speech enhancement or
some other kind of signal processing and
where we have the base on the Deep neur
Network and then we actually get the
back propagation because this is a kind
of basic operation so we actually can
get the derivative so this kind of
approach of jointly optimizing the front
end and the speech equation is one of
the very the cool the active research
area now so this is actually one of the
topic that we our group is actually
quite actively working on
it and the
second uh the advanced topic is s superv
learning I'm very sure that people have
heard the theb the WB to to or some
other s super learning right and this
can be used as pre-training find but
many people actually using this kind of
self supervised learning model as a
feature
representation how to do that we just
you know from the web form and let's say
this one is like the web to or hu or or
whatever s super learning and then we
just do the for computation and then we
just extracting the feature
here this one is turns out to be super
powerful so again people may also using
the fine tuning but this kind of just
extracting a feature itself is super
powerful so this is actually the the the
start to be used as a replacement of the
log fi although it's comput super
expensive and the other kind of cool
direction is again our group is working
on it and one of the th is actually
quite of actively working on it instead
of representing this feature as a
continuous Vector we actually replacing
it as a discrete symbol like after the K
me and so on we can actually convert
this feature to be discreet the sequence
and then now speech qution becomes very
similar to
NLP input is discret so we actually can
use for example machine translation uh
and then you know the machine
translation but input is a speech
discrete token and then output is a kind
of our kind of text and then we just
using the other the machine translation
techniques and so on this is also kind
of advanced other speech feature uh
technique I would say not sure that can
be fly replaced with l F Bank So
currently by the way the the this method
and this method are quite Advanced so
many kind of system are still using the
do F bank because it's very kind of the
efficient computation but I just want to
kind of introduce it and of course the
some of the top topic like s super
learning can be also shown more
discussed in the the later uh so if you
guys don't drop this course
and the the very late the the lectures
including such kind of exciting areas
and so on okay so that's it from the
today's talk so first I kind of spend a
lot of time to explain about Lil filter
bank I try
to avoid to have a lot of mass or signal
processing just know visualize it and
how it has some meaning and so on and I
hope you guys have some kind of sense of
what is the l f that is actually fine
for uh this lecture uh and they uh this
is very complicated I would say the
motivated by signal processing
perceptual property but it's
surprisingly quite working well again
still many other people try to replace
it with the CNN and so on but majority
is still using the the Lan F it's a
power of the signal processing actually
and and but again that still we have a
lot of kind of other research about this
field and so and this time I also add a
reference and one of the
important the remark is that again you
guys are lucky the we also have a the
course in the digital signal processing
in ECE uh that's by the the rich
Professor Rich stand that he's an expert
of this the part so if you want to know
more about deeply about this area I'm
recommended to also take this course
yeah that's it uh any questions